All right, so we're on the top of צדי דלד עמוד א,
Tzadi Dalet Amud Alef, the משנה. Mishnah. Correct? Correct. Okay, the first
subject today is going to be the subject of תנאי, T'nai, of
various conditional statements that are made and when the תנאי T'nai is
considered a good תנאי T'nai or not a good תנאי. T'nai. To
say if a תנאי T'nai is good, תנאי T'nai means that the
action that you've committed to do conditionally will only take effect if
the תנאי T'nai is מקוים, Mekuyam, that's the language of the משנה,
Mishnah, and if the תנאי T'nai that you've that you've made is
somehow not a valid תנאי, T'nai, then the תנאי T'nai is בטל
Batel and that means the action will be valid no matter what,
okay, or the the statement that you make will be valid no
matter what. So let's begin. מתנה שומר חנם להיות פטור משבועה והשואל
להיות פטור מלשלם נושא שכר והשוכר להיות פטורים משבועה ומלשלם. Matneh shomer
chinam lihyot patur mishvuah vehashoel lihyot patur milishalem nose sachar vehasocher lihyot
pturim mishvuah umilishalem.
Okay. So, this is the ארבעה שומרים, Arba Shomrim, right? You've been
introduced to the ארבעה שומרים Arba Shomrim a number of משניות Mishnayot
ago. So if a שומר חנם Shomer Chinam makes a condition that
he will do his שמירה Shmira only if he will be exempt
from taking a שבועה, Shvuah, right, a שומר חנם Shomer Chinam remember
is only חייב Chayav for פשיעה, Pshia, is only חייב Chayav for
negligence, but for any other occurrence such as theft, loss, or an
act of God, he does not have to he does not have
to pay provided that he is that he takes a שבועה. Shvuah.
So let's say the שומר חנם Shomer Chinam says, great, I am
only going to be your שומר חנם Shomer Chinam on the condition
that I don't have to take a שבועה Shvuah if nothing happens
and I just don't have to pay up. Similarly the שואל Shoel
who's at the opposite end of the spectrum from the שומר חנם
Shomer Chinam who has the highest level of responsibility, he's responsible for
basically everything, meaning in his cases in addition not only גניבה ואבידה,
Gneivah Va'aveidah, but also acts of God. So now he says, I
am only going to borrow this object, don't know how this would
happen, right, I'm only going to borrow your object if you exempt
me from payment if any of these things happens. So what about
the borrowing between those two? What? That is the borrower. So the
שואל Shoel is the borrower. Yes. So we're going sort of from
שומר Shomer number one to number four the two extremes and then
the two in the middle, the נושא שכר Nose Sachar and the
שוכר, Socher, the renter and the person who's been paying the person
who's been paid to watch and the renter, they make the condition
that they will only do that activity if they will be exempt
from both swearing and from paying, right, they swear they swear to
the גניבה ואבידה, Gneivah Va'aveidah, it was not stolen or lost, I'm
sorry, they swear to the אונס Ones that an act of God
did not happen and they pay in the case that it was
stolen or lost. So in these cases if the שומר Shomer makes
a makes a תנאי, T'nai, right, he agrees to to do the
שמירה Shmira only on the condition that he doesn't have to do
something that is fundamental to what defines his act of שמירה, Shmira,
what the משנה Mishnah is saying is that's valid, right, that's okay,
one can do that, one can make that kind of condition. Okay.
Now here's the interesting part. The next statement, the part two of
the משנה Mishnah is כל המתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה תנאו בטל.
Kol hamatneh al mah shekatuv batorah t'nao batel.
Anyone who makes a condition
regarding something or against something that the Torah has commanded, right, in
other words meaning they're obligated from the Torah to do this and
they say I will only do it if you do not impose
this obligation on me which is actually a Torah obligation, that תנאי
T'nai is no good. Okay. We'll we'll see an example of this
in the גמרא. Gemara. So that תנאי T'nai is no good and
then they have committed themselves to the activity unconditionally. The גמרא Gemara
is going to raise a question about that because of course the
שומרים Shomrim and their obligations are actually listed in the Torah, so
why is it that the שומר Shomer can make such a condition
when the next statement of the גמרא Gemara is that if one
does so then the תנאי T'nai is בטל, Batel, is no
good. Point three, וכל תנאי שיש מעשה בתחלתו תנאו בטל. Vechol t'nai
sheyesh ma'aseh bitchilato t'nao batel. Any תנאי T'nai in which the action
is stated before the conditional statement. We'll look at רשי, Rashi, that's
how רשי Rashi understands it. That also is an invalid תנאי. T'nai.
Let's take a look at at the רשי. Rashi. Okay. The first
one just says כל המתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה בגמרא מפרש להו,
Kol hamatneh al mah shekatuv batorah begemara mepharesh lehu, the גמרא Gemara
is going to explain it. בגמרא מפרש להו. Begemara mepharesh lehu. Okay,
so so basically רשי Rashi saying yeah just hang on a second
it's coming. Okay. Let's see so let's take a look at the
next רשי. Rashi. כל תנאי שיש בו מעשה בתחלתו. Kol t'nai sheyesh
bo ma'aseh bitchilato.
So any condition in which the action is made before the conditional
statement. רשי Rashi explains. שהקדים מעשה שעליו לעשות לתנאי שהוא שואל ממנו.
shehikdim ma'aseh she'alav la'asos l'tnai shehu sho'el mimenu.
The person states first the מעשה, ma'aseh, right, the action that
he is going to do. He states that before the condition that
he is asking for, right? In other words, that he's saying I
will do this on the condition that. כגון, Kigon, what's our example?
הרי מעשה שלך אם תעשה דבר פלוני. Harei ma'aseh shelcha im ta'aseh
davar ploni. This thing will be yours if you do this. Okay,
so you state this is going to be yours and then you
state the condition. That's no good. Why not? דלא דמי לתנאי בני
גד ובני ראובן, D'lo dami l'tnai Bnei Gad u'Bnei Reuven, because it's
not similar to the תנאי tnai that בני גד ובני ראובן Bnei
Gad u'Bnei Reuven made before the entrance into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
If you remember at the end of פרשת מסעי, Parshat Mas'ei, מטות
Matot I think, right? פרשת מטות. Parshat Matot. Yeah. בני גד ובני
ראובן Bnei Gad u'Bnei Reuven come to משה Moshe and they say,
we want to stay here. We want to stay here in the
land. We'll go, we'll fight, but we want to stay here. And
משה Moshe says, and משה Moshe with some reluctance eventually agrees. Okay,
that model, that story is actually an example of תנאי. tnai. Gloria,
you want to say something? No. No? Okay, just cough. Okay. And
here is the פסוק: pasuk: אם יעברו ונתתם. Im ya'avru u'nesatem. If,
משה Moshe says if you pass before your brothers and help them
conquer the land, then you will be given this land. Okay, so
the conditional statement is the one that comes first. Not you will
get this land if you go and help conquer the land, but
if you help conquer the land, it's an if-then statement, not the
then-if statement. Then you will get this
land. היינו תנאי קודם למעשה. Hainu tnai kodem l'ma'aseh. אם תעשה לי
הדבר הזה אשובה אראה צאנך, Im ta'aseh li hadavar hazeh ashuvah ereh
tzonecha, right? יעקב Ya'akov says to לבן, Lavan, if you do this
thing for me, then I will go and I will, who's the
one who's speaking there? I will go and I will, I will
shepherd your flocks. היינו תנאי ששואל ממנו קודם למעשה שעליו לעשות, Hainu
tnai shesho'el mimenu kodem l'ma'aseh she'alav la'asos, right? That's a תנאי tnai
that you're requesting that I want to do this conditionally before the
action that you are committing yourself to do.
Okay, fine. Now רש''י Rashi says, and let's look at the next
רש''י. Rashi. תנאו בטל. Tna'o batel. What does it mean that the
condition is nullified? והוי מעשה מקוים. V'havei ma'aseh mikuyam. That means the
action, the then statement, is established. ואף על פי שלא קיים, V'af
al pi shelo kiyam, בטל התנאי ולא קיים בעל התנאי את התנאי.
Batel hatnai v'lo kiyam ba'al hatnai es hatnai. That action will take
effect even though the person who made the statement made a condition,
it doesn't matter, that's what it means for the condition
to be invalid. So for example, if משה Moshe had said, you
will get this land if and only if you cross into ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that means whether they did or didn't cross into
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, they would still get the land, okay? Because
it's not a good condition, an invalid condition means the then statement
is going to happen no matter what, even if you don't fulfill
the condition that says if you didn't say it. Okay, so that's
point number three, right? The שומרים shomrim can make a תנאי, tnai,
which seems to be against what they're required to do. You cannot
make a תנאי tnai against what the תורה Torah already commands to
you. And if you make a תנאי tnai in a language in
which you put the then statement before the if statement, that's no
good. התנאי בטל Hatnai batel and you have to do the action.
Point four in the משנה: Mishnah: וכל תנאי שיש מעשה בתחילתו. V'chol
tnai sheyesh ma'aseh bit'chilaso. That's the one I did. Last one: וכל
שאפשר לו לקיימו בסופו והתנה עמו מתחילתו
תנאו קיים. V'chol she'efshar lo l'kaymo b'sofo v'hisna imo mit'chilaso tna'o kayam.
Okay, this is another example. We'll take a look at רש''י Rashi
again. Anything that is possible to do at the end, right, so
an action that is possible and you make a condition of that
initially, that תנאי tnai is good תנאי. tnai. Okay, that was really
clear. So let's take a look at רש''י. Rashi. וכל
תנאי שאפשר לו לקיימו תנאו קיים. V'chol tnai she'efshar lo l'kaymo tna'o
kayam. אם תנאו קודם למעשה הוא, Im tna'o kodem l'ma'aseh hu, right?
That means number one that you have the תנאי, tnai, right, you
did it in the right order. הא אי אפשר לקיימו תנאו בטל
והמעשה קיים. Ha ee efshar l'kaymo tna'o batel v'hama'aseh kayam. However, if
the conditional statement that you make is impossible to fulfill, then. the
תנאי tnai is בטל batel and you have to do the action.
גמרא מפרש לה. Gmara mefaresh la. So for example, let's say you
kept the right order. You made the conditional statement first. You made
the if and then the then. But if, only if the if
is possible, is the תנאי tnai good. Let's say you gave a,
I will do this if, no it has to be the תנאי
tnai first. Or first of all, the תנאי tnai has to be
first, right? If I walk on the moon, if I walk on
the moon, I will bake you a pie. Exactly. Okay. So whether
we consider walking on the moon possible or impossible, right? So if
I, so, good example, right? Okay. If I, the גמרא Gmara is
going to give an example, if I go up to heaven, which
I guess is walking on the moon, right? If I go up
to heaven, then I'll bake you a cake. So you did the
if before the then statement, but what the משנה Mishna is saying
is since your if statement was impossible, אי אפשר לקיימו, i efshar
lekayemo, right? I can't fulfill it, it's a no good תנאי tnai
and you're committed no matter what. Okay. So those are the four
cases in the משנה. Mishna. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gmara. The
גמרא Gmara is going to begin with our first question, which is
how can a שומר, shomer, how can a שומר shomer make a
condition against what the תורה Torah prescribes as the commitment and the
responsibilities of a שומר, shomer, given that we said if you make
a תנאי tnai against what's written in the תורה, Torah, the תנאי
tnai is no good? Right? So that's an immediate contradiction. So the
גמרא Gmara begins, אמאי? amai? Why is that a good תנאי? tnai?
מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה הוא. matne al ma shekatuv baTorah hu.
Right? It's after all an example of making a תנאי tnai against
something that's written in the תורה. Torah. וכל המתנה על מה שכתוב
בתורה תנאו בטל. vechol hamatne al ma shekatuv baTorah tna'o batel. And
the משנה Mishna said in the second part, anyone who makes a
תנאי tnai against what is written in the תורה, Torah, his תנאי
tnai is no good. הא מני? ha mani? So the גמרא Gmara
answers, initially suggests, who's the author of our משנה? Mishna? רבי יהודה
היא. Rabbi Yehuda hi. It's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דאמר בדבר שבממון
תנאו קיים. de'amar bedavar shebemamon tna'o kayam. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
has an exception. Yes, it's true that normally one cannot make a
תנאי tnai against something that's written in the תורה. Torah. However, if
it's a monetary matter, then that תנאי tnai is good. Okay. So
before we get to the proof text, let's think about this a
second. So the שומר shomer says, release me from my obligation to
pay in certain cases, right? Even though the תורה Torah says I
have to pay. Release me from my vow, which means also I'm
not going to have to pay. That is a monetary matter. I'm
trying to get out of a financial obligation. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says, yep, that rule of כל המתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה תנאו
בטל kol hamatne al ma shekatuv baTorah tna'o batel does not apply
in monetary cases. Okay.
Rabbi Dov, you look deep in thought. Yeah, no, in other words
as opposed to different איסורא. issura.
Correct. Correct. As opposed to something exactly. I'm just trying to imagine
some type of condition, if I don't know if לאו lav or
עשה. aseh. Well, let's keep it with a לאו, lav, right? Okay,
a לאו, lav, right. If I don't, if I don't have to
keep שבת, Shabbat, right, then I'll give you a million bucks. Go
to your local rabbi. If I don't have to keep שבת, Shabbat,
I'll contribute to the capital campaign. Exactly, exactly. Okay, good. So this
is the position of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא, detanya, we have
a ברייתא braita that says, אמר לאשה הרי את מקודשת לי על
מנת שאין לי עליך שאר כסות ועונה הרי זו מקודשת ותנאו בטל
דברי רבי מאיר. Amar le'ishah harei at mekudeshet li al menat she'ein
li alayich she'er ksut ve'onah harei zu mekudeshet vetna'o batel divrei Rabbi
Meir. You see now why isn't that a case of a מעשה
ma'aseh before the תנאי? tnai?
That is a good question. And it's always like that with קידושין.
kiddushin. הרי את מקודשת לי בתנאי ש. Harei at mekudeshet li bitnai
she. Yeah.
So I was thinking about that. You always say it that way,
I'll do this on the condition that. It's precisely now the opposite.
So just a thought that's mulling around my mind. Yeah, I get
that. Okay. Well, it says it's void. So that's true, but it's
void for this reason. Not for, right, it has void for מה
שמתנה בתורה. ma shematne baTorah. Exactly.
Okay, so let's, we're going to have a similar question on this
in a
moment. Wait, in the משנה, Mishna, that's the first example, so maybe
that overrides the following. Well, it shouldn't, it should still have to
follow all the rules, right? In other words, what I mean is
that it got denied for the first reason, so we didn't even
get to the other reasons about the order, right? But we're going
to have an opinion that says it's okay. So let's see. Okay.
So a man says to a woman, you are betrothed to me
on the condition that you have no you can... not extract from
me שאר כסות ועונה. She'er Kesut VeOnah. We'll give it
the more often used translation. שאר She'er being
מזונות Mezonot food, כסות Kesut being clothing, עונה Onah is her sexual
rights. הרי זו מקודשת ותנאו בטל. Harei Zo Mekudeshet VeTna'o Batel. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says, yeah, כל המתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה תנאו
בטל. Kol HaMatneh Al Mah SheKatuv BaTorah Tna'o Batel. Man is obligated
to provide these things for his wife and she is מקודשת Mekudeshet
no matter what, the תנאי Tnai is no good. That's רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, okay? רבי יהודה אומר בדבר שבממון תנאו קיים. Rabbi Yehuda
Omer BiDvar SheBeMamon Tna'o Kayam. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no, if
it's financial then the תנאי Tnai is good and she's only מקודשת
Mekudeshet in this particular on the condition that he doesn't have to
provide for her. Provide what? Take a look quickly at רש״י. Rashi.
בדבר שבממון BiDvar SheBeMamon שאר כסות. She'er Kesut. That refers to the
first two, right? The financial support, the feeding and the clothing because
the sexual rights is not financial,
at least we hope not, right?
So in the case of שאר וכסות She'er VeKesut according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir you can make that is not a good תנאי,
Tnai, she's מקודשת. Mekudeshet. He cannot make a תנאי Tnai I'm not
going to fulfill my financial obligations to you as a husband and
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda he can. Okay, so therefore now
let's go back to the גמרא Gemara suggesting that the author of
our משנה Mishna is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and that's why the
שומר Shomer can say I will be your שומר, Shomer, I'm saying
it backwards again, only if I am released from my financial obligations
to you if something happens to the object. ומי מצית מוקמת לה
כרבי יהודה? Umi Matzit Mokmat Lah KeRabbi Yehuda? אימא סיפא: Eima Seifa:
כל המתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה תנאו בטל. Kol HaMatneh Al Mah
SheKatuv BaTorah Tna'o Batel. אתאן לרבי מאיר. Atan LeRabbi Meir.
Okay, so the problem is what about how can we really say
the משנה Mishna is like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
When the next statement of the משנה Mishna is an unqualified statement:
anyone who makes a condition against what's written in the תורה, Torah,
his תנאי's Tnai no good. Isn't that רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position?
Right? In other words, the statements seem contradictory because רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says if you make a condition against what's written in the
תורה Torah your תנאי Tnai is good if it's financial
and the next statement of the גמרא Gemara is unqualified and seems
to be saying anytime you make a condition against what's written in
the תורה Torah your תנאי Tnai is no good. לא קשיא, Lo
Kashya, not a difficulty. לעולם רבי יהודה היא. LeOlam Rabbi Yehuda Hi.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the author of both statements. סיפא בדבר
שאינו של ממון. Seifa BiDvar She'eino Shel Mamon. Right. Ah, good example,
right? The first one is a financial case. The next statement is
only about ritual
issues, only about איסור והיתר. Issur VeHeter.
Wait a second, not so פשוט. Pashut. אימא סיפא: Eima Seifa: כל
תנאי שיש בו מעשה בתחילתו תנאו בטל. Kol Tnai SheYesh Bo Ma'aseh
BiTchilato Tna'o Batel. מאן שמעת ליה דאית ליה האי סברא? Man Shamat
Leh De'it Leh Hai Sevara? רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. The problem is
the next statement in the משנה, Mishna, right? The later statement in
the משנה Mishna of a תנאי Tnai where the מעשה Ma'aseh statement
is made before the תנאי Tnai statement is no good. Whose הלכה
Halacha is this? It's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. How do we know
that? דתניא אבא חלפתא איש כפר חנניא אמר משום רבי מאיר. DeTanya
Abba Chalafta Ish Kfar Chananya Amar Mishum Rabbi Meir. אבא חלפתא Abba
Chalafta said in the name of רבי מאיר: Rabbi Meir: תנאי קודם
למעשה הרי זה תנאי, Tnai Kodem LeMa'aseh Harei Zeh Tnai, מעשה קודם
לתנאי אינו תנאי. Ma'aseh Kodem LeTnai Eino Tnai. Wait a second, רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir is the author of the third statement in the
משנה Mishna that the only תנאי Tnai that's a good תנאי Tnai
is that you make the conditional statement first. So how can you
have the first half of the משנה Mishna be רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda and the second half be רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir when it's
unstated? It has to be consistent. It has to be either רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda or רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it can't split it.
Right, if it's an anonymous statement it has to be consistent. Has
to be consistent. Okay, גמרא Gemara comes up with a new solution.
אלא כולה רבי מאיר היא. Ela Kula Rabbi Meir Hi. No, the
whole משנה Mishna is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ושאני הכא VeShani Hacha
and the case of שומר Shomer is an exceptional case. דמעיקרא לא
שביד נפשיה DeMe'ikara Lo Sha'abed Nafsheh because what happened at the very
initial stages he did not obligate himself. Let's take a look at
רש״י. Rashi. Nice explanation here, a little long.
אפילו תימא רישא דקתני מתנה שומר חנם להיות פטור משבועה רבי
מאיר. Afilu Teima Reisha DeKatani Matneh Shomer Chinam Lehiyot Patur MiShvu'ah Rabbi
Meir.
Okay, that initial statement says רש״י Rashi referring us back, the statement
that for example the שומר חנם Shomer Chinam makes a תנאי Tnai
to be exempt from taking an oath if something happens to the
object, that's also רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. והאי
לאו מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה הוא? VeHai Lav Matneh Al Mah
SheKatuv BaTorah Hu? Wait a second, isn't that making a condition regarding
something written in the תורה? Torah? אלא, Ella, so how do we
resolve this? What is this שוי נפשיה? shavei nafshia? מעיקרא לא שוי
נפשיה, meikara lo shavei nafshia, שאמר לו, sheamar lo, אי אפשי שאהיה
שומר שלך אלא בכך. ee efshi she'eheyeh shomer shelcha ella b'kach. He
says before making any commitment, right? Reuven says to Shimon, be my
שומר חינם shomer chinam on my car. And Shimon says back to
Reuven, no, I don't want to be your שומר shomer unless you
release me from my vow. ושומר לא נחית לשמירה עד דמשך לבהמה.
v'shomer lo nachis l'shmira ad d'mashach l'behema. You don't become a שומר,
shomer, right, until the קנין, kinyan, until the action is actually made
a legally valid action which requires him taking hold of the animal
and doing an act of משיכה meshicha which is an act of
קנין. kinyan. והאי כי משך כבר פירש על מנת שלא עליו שבועה.
v'hai ki mashach kvar pirash amnat shelo alav shvua.
And when he took over the animal, he had already preceded that
with this condition that he's only going to do the שמירה shmira
if he doesn't have to make a שבועה shvua if something happens.
ולא שוי נפשיה לעייולי בתורת שומרים אלא במקצת. v'lo shavei nafshia l'ayeilei
b'torat shomrim ella b'miksas. He's only committed himself to become a partial
שומר, shomer, right? I'm going to become a שומר shomer sort of.
ולמה דירד ירד, u'lma d'yarad yarad, right? And therefore he's only obligated
to that which he obligated himself. Essentially what he's doing he's saying
I don't want to be a biblical שומר חינם. shomer chinam. I
will watch your animal for free with this condition provided that if
something happens to the animal I have no obligations to you at
all. I don't have to go and swear that I wasn't negligent.
Okay. אבל המקדש את האשה, aval hamikadesh es haisha, a man who's
מקדש mikadesh a woman, מכי אמר לה הרי את מקודשת לי, miki
amar lah harei at mekudeshet li, as soon as those words come
out, איקדשה לה, ikadsha lah, she is מקודשת mekudeshet to him. וכי
אמר לה על מנת שאין לי עליך, v'ki amar lah amnat she'ein
li alayich, and when he says provided that I have no financial
obligations to you, מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה, matneh al mah shekasuv
baTorah, that is a case where he's made a condition that's against
the תורה. Torah. Why? דאין אישות לחצאין, de'ein ishut l'chatza'in, there's no
such thing as being half married. I'll be like a little pregnant.
Exactly. You can't be a little married, you can't be a little
pregnant. I'm sort of your husband, theoretically. וכי
תפיס קידושין לגמרי תפיס. v'ki tafis kiddushin l'gamrei tafis. As soon as
the קידושין kiddushin go into effect, they're totally in effect. והוה מתנה
על מה שכתוב בתורה. v'hava matneh al mah shekasuv baTorah. And therefore
that's a תנאי tnai against what's written in the תורה, Torah, right?
So the cases are different, not in that they're using two different
rules, they're using the same rule, but in one case his action
has not qualified to be subject to the rules and the other
one it has, right? Yes. So why is the שומר shomer allowed
to do that? In other words, if in a marriage it comes
automatically as these are the conditions written in the תורה, Torah, so
why is the שומר shomer allowed to accept the title שומר shomer
without the conditions that are written in the תורה? Torah? So what
I would say is essentially he's not accepting the title שומר. shomer.
He's saying I'm going to watch your animal, happy to watch your
animal on the condition that I have no financial obligations. So he
didn't become a שומר shomer until afterwards, right? Correct. But we still
use the word שומר? shomer? What? We use the word שומר shomer
because that's what he's doing, right? But essentially he hasn't committed himself
to all the constraints, right? And therefore when he takes hold of
the animal he's already taken hold of it in this particular more
limited sense of responsibility. But what I'm saying is the husband can't
do that. Right. Husband can't do that because the act of קידושין
kiddushin is already a predefined halachic act. So what we're saying here
is you can be a שומר shomer without being a biblical שומר.
shomer. Essentially, yeah, I guess just saying it's a... it's sort of
a lower level
of... of שמירה. shmira. So like if you're going to do this
for me, you're going to watch my car or whatever... in this
type of situation, it must be like I'm desperate. Like I can't
find anybody else to really be a full שומר shomer for my
car. I'm desperate, I need... so you're going to say to me
like, yeah fine, whatever, I'm not going anywhere, I'm sitting here on
the park bench drinking a cup of coffee, I'll watch your car,
but like don't blame me if someone smashes into it, if somebody
comes and rips it off, if somebody... In other words, right... so
I would say you have no תורה Torah obligation that when you're
a שומר shomer for something you fit into these parameters. It's sort
of like if I make a commitment without playing this game, right,
then I'm obligated as a שומר חינם, shomer chinam, right, in the
way that the תורה Torah says. But if I stipulate beforehand I'm
allowed to do that, okay? I am not allowed or... a man
is not allowed to be מקדש mikadesh a woman, right, which is
a ritual act... partway. There are rules for that, okay? Here the
rules can go into effect but they don't go into effect if
I haven't pre-committed.
Okay? Alright.
Where are we?
Or otherwise I'm leaving it in my garage with no one watching
it. Exactly. So are we accepting that idea from Rabbi Yehuda that
it's only on monetary areas that we're allowed to do this? So
we are no, because what Rabbi Meir is saying is Rabbi Meir
says no, it's true in all cases. כל המתנה על מה שכתוב
בתורה תנאו בטל tnao batel. *Kol hamatneh al mah shekatuv baTorah t'na'o
batel*. However, the first example, the first set of examples in the
first part of the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*, are simply not examples of
that. Okay. I know the two are juxtaposed, but they're not related.
Okay, they're totally separate issues. Okay, fine. תנא
*Tena*, so we're up to you know where we are, Joe?
Okay, we're up to right here. תנא *Tena*. Okay.
Okay, so now we have a ברייתא braita. *Baraita*.
זה
מעיקרא לשעבד נפשיה *Zeh me'ikara l'sha'abed nafshia* is listen, I just want
you I want you to know לכתחילה *lechatchila*, I'm not playing. I'm
not playing. Exactly. So I haven't taken I haven't obligated. Exactly. Exactly.
I'm not playing, but what do you want me to do? This
is a precondition. Exactly. Okay. תנא *Tena*. ומתנה שומר שכר shomer sachar
להיות כשואל *Umatneh shomer sachar lihyot k'sho'el*. במה *Bemeh*? בדברים *Bidvarim*? Okay,
so now this is a really crazy example. שומר חינם shomer chinam,
*Shomer chinam* says you know what? I only want to be your
שומר חינם shomer chinam, *shomer chinam* if you pose on me the
max obligations, right, the obligations of a שואל shoel. *sho'el*, which is
bizarre. So how can that happen? Just by saying it, right? אמר
שמואל בשקנו מידו *Amar Shmuel beshikanu miyado*. Shmuel says no, you have
to have a קניין kinyan. *kinyan*, right? So if the guy agrees,
which why wouldn't he,
and they do a קניין kinyan. *kinyan*, then the שומר shomer I'm
sorry, the שומר שכר shomer sachar. *shomer sachar* is obligated to the
full responsibilities of a of a שואל shoel, *sho'el*. ורבי יוחנן אמר
אפילו תימא בשלא קנו מידו *V'Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu tema beshelo kanu
miyado*. Rabbi Yochanan says no, even if there's not a קניין Kinyan
*kinyan*. Why? בההיא הנאה דקנפיק ליה קלא דאינש מהימן הוא גמיר ומשעבד
נפשיה *Behahi hana'ah d'kanfik leh kala d'inish meheiman hu gamir umeshabed nafshia*.
Rabbi Rabbi Yochanan says something very interesting. If I'm שומר shomer *shomer*,
right, then I actually can get a lot of הנאה *hana'ah*. Right?
Remember the שואל shoel *sho'el*, the relationship between הנאה *hana'ah* and responsibility,
right, it's an inverse relationship. The more responsibility I have, the assumption
is no, it's a direct relationship. It's because I get more הנאה
*hana'ah*. The שואל shoel, *sho'el* can use the object for free, he
has the max responsibility. But the שומר shomer *shomer* so the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* suggests that שומר שכר shomer sachar *shomer sachar* actually can
get a lot more הנאה *hana'ah* than you would think, meaning other
than his salary, because it's going to become known that he's trustworthy.
Okay, so with the fact that there's a קול *kol*, right, there's
an announcement or there's there's the knowledge that he is now a
trustworthy person, person, he can actually obligate himself to that higher level
of responsibility where he pays if an act of God occurs. Okay?
Why would someone want to do that? Exactly for that. They want
to have a good reputation. For the reputation. Exactly. Right? And maybe
next time someone will be willing to lend him an object. Exactly.
So he's not saying I want the right to use it as
long as I'm watching it. No, he's saying I just want the
responsibility. Exactly. Exactly. Which, right, would seem to be crazy. Rabbi Yochanan
says no, I can I can I can see that that one
makes sense. Let's go to the end and then we'll we have
to move on to the next משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. אמר וכל שאפשר
לו לקיימו בסופו *Amar vechol she'efshar lo l'kaymo besofo*. Remember, this was
the idea that if you make a תנאי tnai *t'nai* which is
impossible to fulfill, your תנאי tnai *t'nai* is no your תנאי tnai,
*t'nai* is no good. Only if you make a תנאי tnai *t'nai*
that's possible to fulfill, then what the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says is
if you make a תנאי tnai *t'nai* that's possible to fulfill, then
then then your the תנאי tnai. *t'nai* is a good תנאי tnai
*t'nai*. אמר רב טבלא אמר רב זו דברי רבי יהודה בן תימא
Rabbi Yehuda ben Tema *Amar Rav Tavla amar Rav zo divrei Rabbi
Yehuda ben Tema*. That משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* follows Rabbi Yehuda ben Tema.
וחכמים אומרים אף על פי שאי אפשר לקיימו בסופו והתנה עליו מתחילתו
תנאו קיים *Vachachamim omrim af al pi she'ee efshar l'kaymo besofo vehitnah
alav mitchilato t'na'o kayam*. But חכמים *Chachamim* say no, even if the
condition is impossible, that's a good תנאי tnai. *t'nai*. Here's our example.
דתניא Detanya, הרי זה גיטך *Detanya harei zeh gittech*, and the other
famous על מנת *al manat* cases. This is your divorce. I divorce
you. על מנת שתעלי לרקיע *Al m'nat sheta'ali larakia*, on condition that
you go up to heaven. על מנת שתרדי לתהום *Al m'nat sheterdi
lathom*, on condition that you go down to the depths of the
sea. Those actually are possible now with technology. This one I think
we still can't do. על מנת שתבלי קנה של מאה אמה *Al
m'nat shetivli kaneh shel me'ah amah*, on the condition that you swallow
a rod that's a hundred... hundred אמה long. על מנת שתעברי את
הים הגדול ברגליך, al menat sheta'avri et hayam hagadol beraglayich, on the
condition that you cross the Mediterranean by foot. נתקיים התנאי, nitkayem hatnai,
הרי זה גט, harei zeh get, ולא נתקיים התנאי, velo nitkayem hatnai,
אינו גט. eino get. If the תנאי tnai is fulfilled, that's good
גט. get. תנאי tnai. isn't fulfilled, it's not a divorce. Okay. רבי
יהודה בן תימא אומר, Rabbi Yehuda ben Tema omer, כזה גט. kizeh
get. No, that's a good גט. get. כלל, klal, אמר רבי יהודה
בן תימא, amar Rabbi Yehuda ben Tema, כל שאי אפשר לקיימו בסופו
והתנה עליו מתחילתו אינו אלא כמפליג וקשר, kol she'i efshar lekaymo besofo
vehitna alav mitechilato eino ela kemifliga vekasher, right? רבי יהודה בן תימא
Rabbi Yehuda ben Tema. says, here's
another psychological reading. Any תנאי, tnai right, that's impossible to fulfill and
you make the תנאי tnai. to begin, it's only because you're driving
her crazy and it's כשר, kasher, right? Meaning he's making her miserable.
Right, let's say she wants a divorce, he says, yeah, I'll give
you a divorce if you walk to the ends of the earth.
Okay, it's a good תנאי because that was just there just to
מעטשע metcha her. אמר רב נחמן אמר רב, amar Rav Nachman amar
Rav, הלכה כרבי יהודה בן תימא. halacha keRabbi Yehuda ben Tema. So
now we have a halachic string, the הלכה halacha follows רבי יהודה
בן תימא. That's not a good תנאי. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק,
amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, מתניתין נמי דייקא. matnitin nami dika. That,
you can even see it from the משנה. mishnah דקתני, de'katni, כל
שאפשר לו לקיימו בסופו והתנה עליו מתחילתו תנאו קיים. kol she'efshar lo
lekaymo besofo vehitna alav mitechilato tnao kayam.
The משנה says any תנאי which is possible to fulfill at the
end you make a condition on the beginning, that's a good תנאי.
הא אי אפשר, ha ee efshar, right, the implication of that is
if it's אי אפשר ee efshar to fulfill the condition, תנאו בטל.
Then the תנאי is no good. שמע מינה, shma mina, learn from
here. Okay. Yeah, Gloria? No? Okay.
It's an interesting thing, you know, אינו אלא כמפליג וקשר, eino ela
kemifliga vekasher, in a way, don't you think it's tantamount to saying
that's not a real תנאי. Yeah, yeah, this is exactly what it
is. It's not like it's a תנאי that's אי אפשר לקיימו ee
efshar lekaymo therefore, but אף
על פי כן, af al pi chen, it's כשר. kasher. It's not
really a תנאי. Exactly. You're just torturing someone. Which you could imagine
in a business setting as well as a divorce. Yep, yep, yep.
You're just torturing the person.
Okay. Alright, moving on to the next פרק. perek. Yep. I can't
say that because I just taught the דף daf today. Okay. השואל
פרה ושאלה בעליה עמה ושכר בעליה עמה. hashoel parah vesha'alah ba'aleha imah
vesachar ba'aleha imah.
If one borrows a cow and borrows the labor of the owner
with it, or well, not necessarily only, whatever, he borrows
the owner which could only be for its labor, or he engages
for hire that owner. Okay, so in other words, this is going
to deal with the פסוק pasuk in the תורה Torah where it
says וכי ישאל איש מעם רעהו ונשבר או מת בעליו אין עמו
שלם ישלם. vechi yishal ish me'im re'ehu venishbar o met ba'alav ein
imo shalem yeshalem. If a person borrows an object from someone else
and the object gets broken or dies, if the owner is not
with the animal then he shall pay. אם בעליו עמו, im ba'alav
imo, but if the owner is with him, לא ישלם, lo yeshalem,
right, then you don't have to pay. So the משנה here is
going into that. Right, so someone who borrows a cow and then
borrows the owner or hires the owner. That's number one. שאל הבעלים
או שכרן, sha'al haba'alim o secharan, you borrow, right, you borrow the
labor of the owner or you hire him, ואחר כך שאל את
הפרה ומתה פטור. ve'achar kach sha'al et haparah umetah patur. And then
you borrow the cow and the cow dies, right, dies through an
act of God, you're exempt, שנאמר, shenemar, the פסוק pasuk says אם
בעליו עמו לא ישלם. im ba'alav imo lo yeshalem. Right, if you
have borrowed or if you've engaged both the animal and its owner,
you don't have to pay, that's the פסוק. pasuk. אבל שאל את
הפרה, aval sha'al et haparah, but if you borrowed the cow first,
ואחר כך שאל את הבעלים או שכרן, ve'achar kach sha'al et haba'alim
o secharan, and then you either borrow or hire the labor of
the owner, ומתה, umetah, and the animal dies through an act of
God, חייב, chayav, you're still חייב, chayav, שנאמר, shenemar, בעליו אין עמו
שלם ישלם. ba'alav ein imo shalem yeshalem. If the owner is not
with him then you shall pay. So in other words, the משנה
here is defining what does בעליו עמו ba'alav imo mean. It means
at the time that you engage, that you borrow the animal, you
either have already engaged the owner or you do the two simultaneously.
But if you borrow the cow and then you say, oh, I'm
going to hire you, borrowing the cow took place first, and that
is considered to be a separate act from what you've done to
engage the owner. Okay? So even if the cow dies after you've
hired the owner? Right. The fact that you got the cow first
is what determines this? No, yes, meaning only if you borrow the
cow after... first. So if you
borrowed the cow first, hired the
owner... you
have to pay. Correct, correct. But if, right, this is the one
exception, well, this is the exception that they're saying is directly out
there in the תורה, Torah, if the two happen simultaneously or by
the time you borrow the פרה para you've already engaged the owner,
that is called בעליו עמו Balav Imo and then you don't have
to pay. Exactly what you said, Gloria, except you said the second
case. Okay, so here comes the גמרא. Gemara מכדי דקתני סיפא ואחר
כך שאלה פרה מכלל דרישא דקתני עמה עמה ממש. Michdi de-katani seifa
ve-achar kach sha-ala para mi-kelal de-reisha de-katani ima ima mamash.
So the fact that the second case is the case where first
you borrow the פרה para and then you engage the owner, that's
a case of עמו, Imo, that must mean the first case actually
means simultaneously you borrow the פרה para and either borrow or hire
the labor of the owner. So the גמרא Gemara says: עמה ממש
מי משכחת לה פרה במשיכה ובעלים באמירה? Ima mamash mi meshkachat lah
para be-meshicha u-baalim be-amira? How is that possible? In order to acquire
the rights to the פרה, para, you have to do משיכה, meshicha,
you have to actually do an act of קניין. kinyan, But to
engage the worker, that could be simply a verbal commitment. So how
can a verbal commitment and taking the animal happen simultaneously? What do
you mean? I don't get that question. Okay, the issue is the
following. How can you pull the פרה para and employ verbally simultaneously?
Yeah,
it's assuming those are two separate acts that one takes longer than
the other. Okay. So it's assuming you're not talking very slowly as
you go, and you will work for me tomorrow.
Exactly. Okay, so that could be the second case where you could
do the משיכה meshicha first and then the אמירה amira and that
would work, but they're trying to figure out what is the definition
of the first case if the second case is one preceded the
other. How do things happen simultaneously? So the גמרא Gemara has two
solutions. איבעית אימא כגון דקיימא פרה בחצירו דשואל דלא מיחתרא משיכה. Ibayit
eima kagon de-kaima para be-chatzeiro de-shoel de-la michtara meshicha.
One possibility is when you're engaging in this transaction, the פרה para
is already standing in the property of the שואל. shoel If it's
standing in the property of the שואל, shoel. there's no act of
משיכה meshicha that's necessary, right? You learned earlier on in בבא מציעא
Bava Metzia that a חצר chatzer can be קונה koneh for a
person. So once that happens, the verbal, the entire verbal transaction occurs
and boom, you're both, right, you're both the שואל sho'el, of the
פרה para and בעליו עמו. Balav Imo. Okay, איבעית אימא, Ibayit eima,
another suggestion, דאמר ליה את גופך לא תישאל עד שעת
משיכת פרתך. de-amar lei at gufach lo tishal ad she-at meshichat paratecha.
You know what? This verbal commitment is not going to go into
effect until I've done משיכה meshicha on your פרה. para. So even
though the statement came first, the moment when it became valid was
at the exact same time as when he was מושך moshech the
פרה. para. Okay? So that was sort of a little the גמרא
Gemara going into how do I explain the first case. Now the
גמרא Gemara is going to involve itself in a much more fundamental
question, which is what is our source in the תורה Torah for
these obligations of the four שומרים? shomrim? Okay? If you take a
look at the פסוקים, pesukim, you will notice that they're not quite
so clear. So the גמרא Gemara is going to go through that.
Yeah? Why does he have to do משיכה? meshicha? That's usually if
you're taking ownership, right? So it's also about creating the legal validity
of an action. Okay, so I'll give you an example of this.
At a wedding, when the
husband, what happens at the חתן'ס טיש? chatan's tisch? So the thing
that happens at the חתן'ס טיש chatan's tisch is the husband obligates
himself to the wife in the financial obligations of the כתובה. ketubah.
That's done by someone who's representing the כלה, kallah, let's say in
a traditional setting, let's say the rabbi, who takes his pen and
he gives it to him and the guy picks it up. Okay,
that is the, that is what makes, that's called a קניין. kinyan
קניין kinyan doesn't only happen when something transfers, but it also creates
הלכה halachic validity to an obligation, okay, to something. So the משיכה
meshicha is necessary in order for him, actually in this case it
is kind of like a change of possession, right? In order for
the animal to become the borrower so that he can use that
animal, so that he can borrow it, an act of קניין, this
legal act of קניין needs to take place. Okay, that's why I'm
asking because it would be you have two owners then in a
sense because the person who's loaning it, he's still the owner of
it. He is absolutely still the owner.
Right, correct, correct. So you have to think of your definition of
קניין a little bit more broadly. Okay? All right, so acquisition of
rights. rights for use. Yes, that's a good way of putting it.
You're acquiring the rights in the object through the משיכה. meshikah. Okay.
Yes. Or הגבהה, hagbahah, but if it's a cow it's gonna be
a little harsh. Okay. תנן התם. tnan hatam. So the משנה teaches,
משנה בשבועות. mishna b'shevuot. ארבעה שומרים הם, arba shomrim hen, there are
four types of watchers. שומר חינם והשואל נושא שכר והשוכר, shomer chinam
vehashoel noseh sachar vehasocher, right? שומר חינם, shomer chinam שואל, sho'el נושא
שכר, noseh sachar, שוכר. socher. שומר חינם, shomer chinam, now we get
the rules which you already know. שומר חינם נשבע על הכל. shomer
chinam nishba al hakol. A שומר חינם shomer chinam can swear and
exempt himself from everything
of the following list. והשואל משלם את הכל. vhashoel meshalem et hakol.
A שואל sho'el pays for everything. Whether he swears is irrelevant. נושא
שכר והשוכר, noseh sachar vehasocher, a paid שומר shomer or a renter
נשבעין על השבורה ועל השבורה ועל המתה ומשלמין את האבידה ואת הגניבה.
nishbayin al hashvura v'al hashvura v'al hameta umeshalmim et ha'aveida v'et hagniva.
Someone who's a נושא שכר noseh sachar or שוכר, socher,
they swear regarding an act of G-d that either damaged the animal,
the animal was kidnapped, or it died, and then they don't have
to pay, but they do have to pay if the object was
or the animal, whatever it is, was lost or stolen. מנה הני
מילי? mina hani milei? Where do we know this from? Where in
the תורה Torah do we know this? דתנו רבנן, de-tanu rabbanan, a
rabbi's taught in a ברייתא. Baraita פרשה ראשונה נאמרה בשומר חינם שניה
בשומר שכר שלישית בשואל. parsha rishona neemra b'shomer chinam shniya b'shomer sachar
shlishit b'shoel. Okay.
So the first פרשה, parsha, the first example, which is פסוקים, psukim,
don't have time to go through them inside now. The first set
of פסוקים, psukim, פסוק ו pasuk vav through ח. chet.
That case is the describes a שומר חינם, shomer chinam right? All
it says is that if a person gives someone else something to
watch and it's stolen, okay? It doesn't it doesn't say for free,
okay? The second פרשה parsha is ט tet through יב. yud bet.
Another example, here what's different in the תורה Torah is that it's
talking about an animal. If a person gives another person an animal
to watch,
and and then they give the two conditions, if it if something
happens through an act of G-d, then you can take a שבועה,
shvua, but if it's stolen then you have to pay. And the
third one, which is clear, is יג yud gimel through
יד. yud dalet. Here it says explicitly if you borrow something, right?
And something happens to the animal, an act of G-d, so depending
on בעליו עמו ba'alav imo or אין בעליו עמו, ein ba'alav imo,
you either pay or you're exempt. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara asks
the following question. בשלמא שלישית בשואל מפורש, bishlama shlishit b'shoel meforash,
right? I understand. The third פרשה parsha explicitly says they're talking about
a שואל. shoel, Quote: וכי ישאל איש מעם רעהו ונשבר או מת
בעליו אין עמו שלם ישלם. v'chi yish'al ish me'im re'ehu v'nishbar o
met ba'alav ein imo shalaim yeshalem. תורה's Torah explicit if a person
borrows and the animal is injured or dies, then only then if
the owner was not hired with him, then you pay. אלא ראשונה
בשומר חינם שניה בשומר שכר איפוך אנא? ela rishona b'shomer chinam shniya
b'shomer sachar ipuch ana?
But the first two פרשיות, parshiot, it never said explicitly what type
of שומר shomer. it is. Maybe it's the opposite, right? Maybe the
שומר חינם shomer chinam, does pay if the animal's stolen and the
שומר שכר shomer sachar doesn't. Why not? מסתברא שניה בשומר שכר שכן
חייב בגניבה ואבידה. mistavra shniya b'shomer sachar sheken chayav b'gniva v'aveida.
So the גמרא Gemara answers: טעמא, tama, right? It only makes sense
to say that a שומר shomer, who's paid has more responsibility and
has to pay if the object is stolen.
So the גמרא Gemara then says back: אדרבה! adderaba! On the contrary!
ראשונה בשומר שכר. rishona b'shomer sachar.
No, I want to say the first פרשה parsha is שומר שכר.
shomer sachar Why? שכן משלם תשלומי כפל בטוען טענת גנב. sheken meshalem
tashlumei kefel b'toen ta'anat ganav.
Because, here's an interesting case, right? Let's say let's say the שומר
actually is responsible, and he swears, he swears that the object was
stolen. Actually, really he stole it. So the גמרא Gemara tells tells
us elsewhere that through reading the פסוקים psukim together that he actually
has to pay כפל, kefel, he has to pay double, okay? Which
is a penalty, right? In other words, a שומר שכר shomer sachar
if if I'm a hired a hired guardian, right? A hired watcher.
And the animal's stolen. I have to pay for the stolen animal.
What am I paying? I'm paying for the I'm paying for the
value of the animal. Let's say I'm a שומר חינם shomer chinam
and I say, oh, the animal was stolen, right? If I say
the animal was stolen as a שומר חינם, shomer chinam I don't
have to pay, right? So if I swear to that, I say
it was stolen and they find out, yeah, I actually took it,
I actually have to pay double, okay? So there's a higher penalty
for theft if I'm a שומר חינם shomer chinam who claims theft
and then I get out of paying it, than a שומר שכר
shomer sachar? who claims theft and pays, okay? So the payments are
different.
I'll say one
more... So there's no כפל kefel for a שומר. There's no כפל
kefel for- there's no כפל kefel for- listen if the object was
stolen and I'm a שומר שכר shomer sachar and I come straight
out and I say the object is stolen, I just pay, right?
Because I didn't fulfill, there was a problem with my שמירה. shmira.
That's יסום, yesom, right? But if the object was not stolen and
I'm a שומר חינם and I pay to get off- and I
swear to get off scot-free and then you find out that I
actually held on to the animal myself, then I'm a גנב, gannav,
right? Then I'm considered a גנב gannav and I have to pay
the normal fine of a גנב, gannav, which is double. And if
I'm a שומר שכר shomer sachar and I swear- I don't get
off if the animal is stolen so it doesn't matter. So but
what if I stole the animal? It doesn't matter. If the animal
is stolen I can't exempt myself. But does he pay double? Why
would he pay double? שומר שכר? shomer sachar No, if I'm a
שומר שכר shomer sachar and I say the animal was stolen, even
if I stole it, I do not pay double. That was what
I wanted to know. That's unbelievable. Isn't that שבועה shvuah though also
that and I didn't steal it? No, no, because I can't swear
as a שומר שכר shomer s'char, that I didn't steal it because
it doesn't matter. I'm on the hook for theft. I'm on the
hook anyhow. So he's not considered a thief. So the כפל kefel
is linked to the שבועה. shvuah. In a way,
the כפל kefel I would say is linked to being someone who,
right, who's נשבע nishba that it wasn't stolen and that exempts me.
Okay? So
it doesn't hold up. This is what the גמרא Gemara is suggesting.
Actually, the tougher case is the first case rather than the second,
right? Because in the event that you claim that it was stolen
and try to exempt yourself and you're the one who stole it,
you have to pay double. So your monetary penalty is twice. But
the שומר שכר shomer s'char is not considered a thief? It doesn't
matter. Whether- if the animal is stolen, the rule is you only
pay- doesn't matter. I mean, he can't take a שבועה shvuah in
that circumstance, right? If you say it was stolen, I don't care
if it was stolen by- you can't take a שבועה. shvuah. Okay,
so the שבועה shvuah won't exempt you. Okay. So, okay, אפילו
הכי. afilu hachi. So the גמרא Gemara says despite that, still the
שומר חינם is the first פרשה. parshah. קרן בלא שבועה עדיפא מכפלא
בשבועה. keren belo shvuah adifa mikfela bishvuah. Because paying the קרן keren
without having to swear is still- would still be preferable than paying
double with- with swearing, meaning with swearing falsely. תידע דהא שבק כל
הנאה שלו ואינו משלם אלא קרן. teida deha shavek kol hana'ah shelo
ve'eino meshalem ela keren. What's our proof? A שואל, who has the
greatest benefit, he only pays a קרן, keren, right? So the sort
of the top penalty for שמירה shmira is קרן. keren.
Okay.
Yes, meaning that business of טוען טענת גנב to'ein ta'anas gannav is
really outside of- that's outside of exactly as- as Rabbi Dov said,
that's outside the parameters of being a שומר, that's really about- that's
really about actually stealing. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
Okay, folks, we have three minutes. Okay, but we started a few
minutes late. והשואל כל הנאה שלו? vehasho'el kol hana'ah shelo?
Wait a second. What do you mean the שואל gets pure benefit?
והא בעי מזונות. veha ba'ei mezonot.
He has to feed the animal, right? I still pay if I
borrow an object because now I'm the one who feeds it. I'm
not going to say I'm borrowing your animal and you're feeding it.
דאיתניהו באגמא. de'itneihu be'agma. No,
it happens to be let's say I live in a place that-
where, you know, the animal can graze for free. So then I
don't have to pay מזונות. mezonot. והא בעי נטירה? veha ba'ei netirah?
Let's say, but wait a second, I have to watch the animal.
בנטירה דמתא. benatira demata. If there's a city watch that already watches
the animal, there's walls around it. Yeah, exactly. Well, walls doesn't help
with the people inside. Oh, no. But my animal goes and grazes
out in the public field and there's someone who's already watching all
the animals. ואיבעית אימא לא תימא כל הנאה שלו אלא אימא רוב
הנאה שלו. ve'iba'it eima lo teima kol hana'ah shelo ela eima rov
hana'ah shelo. The other suggestion which seems to me more logical is
when we said all he gets only or all benefit, it doesn't
really mean all, it means most, right? He gets the most benefit.
ואיבעית אימא בשאילת כלים. ve'iba'it eima bish'ilat keilim.
The other possibility is we're not talking- we're just talking about something
like if I borrow an object, right, not an animal, in which
case I don't gotta do anything, right? It's in my house, it's
being watched, I don't have to feed it. So- so in that
case I get all benefit. Okay. Period. Next thing. נושא שכר והשוכר
נשבעין על השבורה ועל השבויה ועל המתה ומשלמין את האבדה ואת הגנבה.
nosei sachar vehasokher nishba'in al hashvurah ve'al hashvuyah ve'al hametah umeshalmin et
ha'avedah ve'et hagnievah. Now, let's get to the fundamental rule about a
שומר שכר shomer s'char, and a renter. They swear regarding accidents, what
kind of accidents, the animal was injured or was kidnapped or it
died. or dies and they pay for if the animal was lost
or stolen. בשלמא גניבה. Bishlama gneivah.
Okay, where am I getting this from? I know that it's גניבה
gneivah that he's responsible for גניבה gneivah דכתיב dikhtiv because it's written
in the תורה: Torah: אם גנב יגנב מעמו ישלם לבעליו. Im ganov
yiganeiv mei'imo yishaleim l've'alav. If the animal is stolen, he has to
pay. אלא אבידה מנלן? Ela aveidah minalan? But where do we know
if the animal was lost? The תורה Torah never says נאבד, ne'evad,
it only says נגנב. nignav.
דתניא, DeTanya, so we have a ברייתא braisa, that says אם גנב
יגנב אין לי אלא גניבה אבידה מנין. im ganov yiganeiv ein li
ela gneivah aveidah minayin.
The פסוק pasuk says if it's stolen, so I know that he
pays for theft. How do I know that he pays for אבידה?
aveidah? תלמוד לומר אם גנב יגנב מכל מקום. Talmud lomar im ganov
yiganeiv mikol makom. So we have the double language. The double language
says if it's stolen in any way, meaning stolen or lost, okay?
It's one of these the emphatic it was stolen away includes אבידה,
aveidah, correct. It's stole away, it's stole away exactly. הני ניחא למאן
דאמר לא אמרינן דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם אלא למאן דאמר אמרינן
דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם מאי איכא למימר? Hani nichla leman de'amar
lo amrinan dibra torah k'lashon b'nei adam ela leman de'amar amrinan dibra
torah k'lashon b'nei adam mai ika l'meimar? So now the גמרא Gemara
says very interesting, that use of the emphatic and being able to
make a דרשה drasha on the double language, on the emphatic, that's
only if you're of the position that says the תורה Torah doesn't
speak the way normal people speak, right? Meaning that when the תורה
Torah uses that emphatic, the תורה Torah actually is there to give
you room to make a דרשה. drasha. But what if you're something
that, what if you say that the תורה Torah does speak like
normal people speak? And when people speak emphatically, all they mean to
be is emphatic about one thing, about one thing. If it's stolen
and I mean stolen, right? That's how normal people speak. Right. So
then you can't use it for a דרשה. drasha. אמרי דמערבא, Amrei
d'ma'arava,
so over there in the west in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they
say קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. No, it's a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer.
ומה גניבה שקרובה לאונס משלם אבידה שקרובה לפשיעה לא כל שכן? Uma
gneivah shekrova l'ones m'shaleim aveidah shekrova lipshiya lo kol sheken? If I'm
responsible for paying for theft, and theft is really pretty close to
something that's not in my control, if in that case I have
to pay, if the object gets lost, which is kind of similar
to my being negligent, how much more so should I have to
pay? So once I teach you that you have to pay for
גניבה, gneivah, of course you have to pay for אבידה. aveidah. So
it's a very good קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Yes, nice קל וחומר.
kal v'chomer. That's what they say in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ואידך
מילתא דאתי בקל וחומר טרח וכתב לה קרא. V'idach milta d'ati b'kal
v'chomer tarach v'chtav lah kra. Ah,
there's a good קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. What do I need the
פסוק pasuk for? Why you telling me I learn from גנב יגנב?
ganov yiganeiv? Ah,
because sometimes even though we have a קל וחומר kal v'chomer the
תורה Torah bothers doing it anyhow, the תורה Torah bothers to telling
us anyhow.
Okay, that's that point, okay? So now we know that the שומר
שכר, shomer s'char. we now have a reason, a קל וחומר kal
v'chomer or a double language in the פסוק pasuk to teach us
that the שומר שכר shomer s'char has to pay גניבה ואבידה. gneivah
va'aveidah. Okay, final point I think. ושואל משלם את הכל. V'sho'el m'shaleim
es hakol. Now, you told me that the הלכה halakha is that
a שואל has to pay for any act of God. בשלמא שבורה
ומתה דכתיב. Bishlama shvura umeisa dikhtiv.
I know that from the תורה Torah they have to pay if
the animal is injured or dies because the תורה Torah says וכי
ישאל איש מעם רעהו ונשבר או מת. v'khi yish'al ish mei'im rei'ehu
v'nishbar o meis.
It says if the animal's injured, right, if it breaks, let's say
it's an object, if it breaks or dies, I have to pay.
But what about אלא שבויה בשואל מנלן? ela shvuya b'sho'el minalan?
How do we know that if the animal's kidnapped, right, I still
have to pay? Or I guess the object is kidnapped. וכי תימא
נילף משבורה ומתה? V'khi teima neilaf mishvura umeisa? Now, let's say, ah,
when it says injured or dies it also includes kidnapped, we can't
say that. מה לשבורה ומתה שכן אונס דסליק אדעתיה תאמר בשבויה שכן
אונס דלא סליק אדעתיה. Ma lishvura umeisa sheken ones d'salik adateih tomar
bishvuya sheken ones d'lo salik adateih. Wait a second, if we're talking
about acts of God that I expect could happen, right, things that
happen despite me, right, being injured and and dying, that that would
occur to me, right? And therefore I understood that as part of
my condition. But kidnapped? For goodness sake, right? That's not something ever
would have thought of and therefore on some level I didn't commit
to.
Never would have occurred to me. Never would have occurred to me
when I took the job. Right, exactly. אלא נאמר שבורה ומתה בשואל
ונאמר שבורה ומתה בשומר שכר. Ela ne'emar shvura umeisa b'sho'el v'ne'emar shvura
umeisa b'shomer s'char. מה להלן שבויה עמו אף כאן שבויה עמו. Ma
lahalan shvuya imo af kan shvuya imo. So we're going to learn
from a היקש, heikesh, right?
So it says שבורה ומתה shvura umeisa here, it says שבורה ומתה
shvura umeisa when it comes to the שומר שכר, shomer s'char but
it also says שבויה shvuya with the שומר שכר. So I can
learn from the שומר שכר to include שבויה shvuya here. איכא למיפרך
מה לשומר שכר שכן לפטור תאמר בשואל שכן לחיוב. Ika l'mifrach ma
lishomer s'char sheken liftor tomar b'sho'el sheken l'chiyuv.
Wait a second, the two cases are not analogous. When it comes
to the שומר שכר I'm lift... שבורה, shevurah, שבויה, shvuyah, ומיתה umitah
to tell me the cases that are exempt. But with a שואל,
I'm listing them as the cases in which you're obligated. Okay? So
this is no good, meaning how can we make an analogy when
the הלכה halacha is the opposite, right? In one case it's to
exempt you, and in the other case it's to obligate you. אלא
כרבי נתן. Ela k'Rabbi Natan. But
the source is Rabbi Natan.
דתניא, DeTanya, רבי נתן אומר, Rabbi Natan omer, או לרבות שבויה. o
l'rabos shvuyah.
So it's the פסוק pasuk is ונשבר או מת, v'nishbar o meis,
so Rabbi Natan says that word או o is there, it's not
necessary, it's there to teach us to include the שבויה. shvuyah. האי
או מיבעי ליה לחלק. Hai o mibay'lei l'chalek.
So the גמרא says back, no, I need the או o if
it's stolen or if it's broken, if it's injured or dies, I
need that to tell us that those are two unique cases. דסלקא
דעתך אמינא D'salka da'atach amina I might have thought, עד דמיתברא ומיתה
לא מיחייב, ad d'mitbra umeisa lo mechayaiv, קא משמע לן. kamashma lan.
I might have thought, right, here's what does or do? Right? Or
says if A happens or B happens, right? So the word or
is necessary why? So that you don't think only if A and
B happen I have to pay. So I need that or, I
need that או o to tell me if it dies or is
injured I have to pay. But it's not conjunctive, it doesn't mean
and. Right. The or is necessary to tell me that it's not
and. If I didn't have the or, I might have thought and,
even though it's a little bit crazy.
הניחא לרבי יונתן אלא לרבי יאשיה מאי איכא למימר? Ha nicha l'Rabbi
Yonatan, ela l'Rabbi Yoshiya mai ika l'meimar? That works for Rabbi Yonatan
and the following, but for Rabbi Yoshiya what do you want to
say? דתניא, איש אשר יקלל את אביו ואת אמו, ish asher yekaleil
et aviv v'et imo, אין לו אלא אביו ואמו אביו בלא אמו
אמו בלא אביו מניין? ein lo ela aviv v'imo, aviv b'lo imo,
imo b'lo aviv minayin? So we have a פסוק pasuk that says
if a person curses their mother and father, right, then they're put
to death. So says the ברייתא, how do I know that it
means the father or the mother? Meaning, maybe it means the father
and the mother. How do I know if you curse just one
of your parents that you're going to be put to death? תלמוד
לומר, Talmud lomar, אביו ואמו קלל. aviv v'imo kileil. Right? Because the
end of the פסוק pasuk says אביו ואמו קלל. aviv v'imo kileil.
The word קללה klalah at the beginning of the פסוק pasuk is
connected to the father, יקלל את אביו ואת אמו, yekaleil et aviv
v'et imo, and the word קללה klalah at the end of the
פסוק pasuk is connected to אמו imo and is juxtaposed to the
father. So we have cursing the father at the beginning of the
פסוק, pasuk, cursing the mother at the end of the פסוק, pasuk,
that means if you curse either of them.
קלל אמו, Kileil imo, אביו ואמו קלל, aviv v'imo kileil, אביו קלל,
aviv kileil, אמו קלל, imo kileil, right? So at the end it
comes out that if you curse the mother or the father.
דברי רבי יאשיה. Divrei Rabbi Yoshiya. That's Rabbi Yoshiya. רבי יונתן אומר,
Rabbi Yonatan omer, משמע שניהם כאחד ומשמע אחד בפני עצמו עד שיפרוט
לך הכתוב יחדיו. mashma shneihem k'echad u'mashma echad bifnei atzmo ad sheyifrot
l'cha hakatuv yachdav. So Rabbi Yonatan says, no, couldn't mean either. The
only reason when we know that something is together that both you
need both A and B is if the תורה Torah says the
word יחדיו yachdav explicitly. Okay?
So therefore according to, let's just take this back, according to Rabbi
Yonatan,
that word or is there to teach us on the case of
שבויה, shvuyah, but according to Rabbi
Yoshiya, that word or is there to teach us A or B.
אפילו תימא רבי יאשיה לחלק הכא לא צריך. Afilu teima Rabbi Yoshiya,
l'chalek hacha lo tzarich. So no, even if you want to say
according to Rabbi Yoshiya who says the or is necessary to make
two cases, here it's not necessary. מאי טעמא סברא הוא Mai ta'ama
s'vara hu because it's logical. מה לי קטלה כולה מה לי קטלה
פלגא. mah liktla kula, mah liktla palga. What's the difference if the
whole animal is killed and what's the difference if half the animal
is killed? In other words,
once I say if the animal is injured then you have to
pay, it's obvious that if the animal dies you have to pay.
Therefore that or is therefore that or is there to teach me
שבויה. shvuyah. Okay, I'm sorry that was like really rushed at the
end here.